Guide to the Dorothea K. Almond Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Dorothea K. Almond papers
1936-1998
1960-1998
SC0663
Almond, Dorothea K.
Almond, Gabriel A. (Gabriel Abraham), 1911-2002
18 Linear feet
Papers include correspondence, newsletters, memos, reports, articles, minutes, and other materials pertaining to childcare at Stanford, child welfare in general, and other social and civic issues, 1960-1998. Some of the minutes and other records are from the Children's Center of the Stanford Community. The collection also includes letters from Gabriel Almond, 1936 and 1947.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Information about Access
This collection is open for research.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
Dorothea Kaufmann Almond, longtime child and family advocate, grew up in Cologne, Germany, and moved to the United States in 1934 to study at Teachers College, Columbia University, where she earned a master's degree in 1941. She moved to Palo Alto in 1963 with her husband, Stanford professor Gabriel Almond. She served as chair of the Committee on Childcare at Stanford from 1969 to 1977, was co-director of the Stanford Childcare Resource and Referral Center from 1978 to 1986, and was a consultant on childcare to the dean of student affairs from 1979 to 1986. Almond was also active in civic affairs as a member of the League of Women Voters and co-chair of a committee affiliated with the league on juvenile justice issues from 1988 to 1991. She died on December 5, 2000.
Description of the Collection
Papers include correspondence, newsletters, memos, reports, articles, minutes, and other materials pertaining to childcare at Stanford, child welfare in general, and other social and civic issues, 1960-1998. Some of the minutes and other records are from the Children's Center of the Stanford Community. The collection also includes letters from Gabriel Almond, 1936 and 1947.
Access Terms
Almond, Dorothea K.; Almond, Gabriel A. (Gabriel Abraham), 1911-2002; Children's Center of the Stanford Community.; Child care services.; Day care centers.; Nursery schools.
Collection Contents
- Papers, Accession ARCH-2002-254
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Magazines (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Child Care Policy (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Child Care Policy, continued (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Child Care Stanford (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Child Development (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Child Welfare (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Policy (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Childcare (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - CCSU etc. (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Child Care Policy, etc. (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - [2 smaller boxes, one containing materials on Palo Alto childcare] (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous files (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous files (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Dissertation (D. Almond) 1939 – photocopy (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Publications / Research video project (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Childcare (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, clippings, articles, reports, flyers, and publications re childcare at Stanford, in Palo Alto, and in general (Box 10, Folder 1)
- Papers, Accession ARCH-2003-017
  - Sand Hill projects, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Parent Voices for Child Care Retreat, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Freshman Seminar (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Campus Report (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Unitarian Church (newsletter, sermons) 1967-70 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Gunn High – careers and drugs materials, 1964-68 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - League of Women Voters 1969-71, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - National Council on the Aging (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Symposiums, Gunn High School, 1960s (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Trust and estate planning (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Housing (LWV) 1960s (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - NAACP, PA-Stanford Branch, newsletter Feb. 1971 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Wedding announcements (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Susan – African study (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Health News Feb. 1970 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Calendar 1969 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Nesbitt, Michael – Children with Psychological Disturbances, ca. 1965 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Change in Higher Education, Mar-Apr 1970 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - The Graduate, [magazine for college seniors] 1972 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Reader’s Digest Sept. 1971 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Education of the Culturally Different, a Multi-Cultural Approach, by Jack D. Forbes, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Council on Child Care at Stanford, newsletters, memos, etc., 1977-80 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence from Gabriel Almond, 1936 and two articles (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Arastradero Road Project (1 of 2) 1978-80 [includes other topics] (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Arastradero Road Project (2 of 2) 1966-78 [includes other topics] (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Stanford Faculty Women’s Club (mostly newsletters) 1973-76 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Palo Alto City Council – Old Trace Road, 1967-68 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Friends Committee on Legislation newsletters 1972-85 and information on the Southern Poverty Law Center (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Clippings – war on poverty (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - English clippings, etc. (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - City of Palo Alto (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Co-op material and misc. Stanford child care items (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Yosemite (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Unicameral Reform (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Palo Alto/Stanford planning 1974 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Almond Scholarship – sale of painting (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Old Trace Road (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Miscellaneous travel materials (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - June 2, 1976 (G’s retirement, dedication of Dorothea Almond Library) (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Stanford housing, 1967-75 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Letters from Gabriel 1947 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Miscellaneous notes, lists (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Plans – Stanford West (includes some Stanford child care items) (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - The Center for Health Training, workshop on children’s health in day care, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Child care history at Stanford (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Committee on Services to Students, Escondido Village Task Force, Report on Escondido Village, Sept. 1978 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - California childcare resource and referral network (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - League of Women Voters Membership Handbook (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - PTA Board Gunn High School, newsletters, minutes, 1966-68 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Women in Politics (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - CCSC Board [Children’s Center of the Stanford Community], minutes, 1977-78 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Family day care (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Employment of women report [clippings only] (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - California Child Care Resource and Referral Network, 1988 conference (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - AIDS & stigma (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Arboretum / Get Well Room (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Children’s Services (assorted publications) (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Intergenerational Project (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Health letters (3 different newsletters), 1987-97 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Almond & Craig, “Cooperative Child Care at Stanford” (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Asilomar (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Miscellaneous items (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Life Career Simulation Game, 1967 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Santa Clara Valley Democratic Coalition (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Sources on childcare at Stanford [was in envelopes marked for Randy Bean and Doug Dupen] (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Samoff, Rachel, “Report on Current Status and Future Plans for the Moffett Child Care Center,” Dec. 1980 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Doug Dupen to Randy Bean, 6/14/1993 [author of S&T article] (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Families in Transition, 1/31/87 – notes (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - CCSC, 1971-93 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Photographs, D. Almond 1976? (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Lally, J. Ronald, “Minimizing the Trauma of Separation when Leaving a Young Child with a New Caregiver” 1985 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - SNAP (Stanford New After-School Program) 1976-77 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Childcare committee, Stanford Faculty Women’s Club (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Arboretum Center’s Get Well Room (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - New childcare center (300 Quarry Rd), 1986-89 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Children’s Center of the Stanford Community – outline for article or program (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Ritchie, Kathleen E. “Status of Childcare Stanford University” 1991 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Historical sources [for Doug Dupen] (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Day Care licensing (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Nomination letters for Cuthbertson Award (for Almond & Craig) (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Miner, Anne, text of talk at child care retreat/conference, 5/8/84 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Craig, Gordon & Phyllis – party 1979 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Stanford childcare – brochures (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - CCSC photographs (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Notes for talk on childcare (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Phyllis’ 80th – comments by DKA, 1998 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Assorted other issues (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - S.U. miscellany (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Childcare – not local (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Local childcare resources 1977-97 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Bing School, 1985-87 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Future is Now: S.U. Centennial Forum, 1990 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Shapiro, Harold T. & Vivian B., “Safe Harbors for All Our Children” (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Craig, P., “A Question of Priorities” (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - S.U. childcare – miscellaneous, 1972-87 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Arboretum Children’s Center (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - S.U. Child and Family Services (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - S.U. Childcare Resource Center (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Miscellaneous notes (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, 1960s-70s (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, 1980s (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, 1990s (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence, n.d. and fragments (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Clippings – not childcare (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Clippings – childcare (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Clippings (original) – childcare (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Generations United [Child/Elder Care model] (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - Generations United (pubs) (Box 6, Folder 22)
General note
A substantial part of the collection is unprocessed.